Lanjing Liu

College of Design and Innovation Tongji University Yangpu, Shanghai, 200082, China

(+86)13310115308liulanjing@tongji.edu.cn https://liulanjing.com/

Research Interests

Design Education For Children And Youth: I earned extensive teaching experience with children and youth to help them understand, learn about design and develop other qualities or skills, e.g., empathy, sense of place, digital literacy.

User Research: I gained insight into the physical or psychological difficulties of special people (e.g. young women with bulimia, one-foot disabled people) by different methods and addressed their problems through design.

Co-Design: I worked with children and educators to design different design teaching tools, both online and offline.

Education

Tongji University, Shanghai, China M.A. in Design History and Theory

GPA:4.45 / 5.00, Advisor: Prof. Lei Zhang

Jiangnan University, Wuxi, China

B.E. in Industrial Design

Chiba University, Chiba, Japan

Exchange Student in Industrial Design

09/2020 - 06/2023 (expc.)

09/2016 - 06/2020

09/2018 - 02/2019

Research Experience

Action Research On Promoting Youth Empathy Through Design Thinking Workshop

Research Center for Design Education and Pedagogy, Tongji University Lead Researcher, team of 3, advised by Prof. Lei Zhang and Prof. Qi Wang 2021.05-2021.09

- Conducted three-cycle action research over three-month with a total of 40 children.
- · Identified design requirements with children, educators through formative study (interviews, observations) and codesign.
- · Designed and developed the DetectiveMap, a card-based teaching tool to promote children's empathy in design workshops or design activities.
- Implemented a preliminary user study with 12 children and their parents to examine the effectiveness of the tools.

A Study Of Design In General Education In The UK

Research Center for Design Education and Pedagogy, Tongji University Researcher, team of 2, advised by Prof. Lei Zhang

2021.11-2022.11

· Collected and organized nearly 100 different documents - archival records, research reports, newspaper reports, speech and conference notes and articles discussing the entry of design education into general education in the UK.

- · Outlined the twenty-year history of design into the UK general education led by Bruce Archer and Ken Baynes.
- Investigated the synergies between design education and design research.

Teaching Experience

Designer Of Community

Summer 2022

Lecturer, Online Course, 9 Students, 2 Weeks

Shanghai Youth Institute of Design and Innovation

- Developed course syllabus and completed teaching independently.
- The syllabus and teaching tools will be implemented in primary schools in Shanghai.

Detective In The Community

Summer 2021

Lecturer, Offline Course, 15 Students, 1 Week

Shanghai Youth Institute of Design and Innovation

- Led a teaching team to develop the syllabus, teaching tools and collaborate with the community.
- Conducted indoor and outdoor teaching activities with 15 children.

The 5th Shanghai Youth Innovation And Entrepreneurship Team Action

2021

Teaching Assistant, Online Course, 1 Month

Shanghai Youth Academy of Sciences

- Helped students to rethink and iterate on projects from a design perspective.
- Students' projects were exhibited at the China International Import Expo 2021.

Patents & Software Copyrights

Patents

A Sketch Recognition and Generation Method based on Raspberry Pi and Recurrent Neural Network. 2020.

China National Invention Patent. Application No. 202011322789.4

A Sentiment Analysis and Visualization Method Combining Video and Pop-Ups. 2019.

China National Invention Patent. Application No. 201910287517.6

Software Copyrights

Enterprise Network Opinion Analysis and Visualization Software. 2019.

China Software Copyright. Registration No. 2019SR0428088

Language

Native Chinese (Mandarin)

Fluent English (ILETS 6.5)

Skills

Research: Interview, Survey, Participatory Design, Action Research, Thematic Analysis

Design: User Experience Design (Figma, Sketch), 3D Modelling and Rendering (Cinema 4D, Rhino 3D), Graphic Design (Adobe Products)